{"tossups": [{"question": "One character in this musical exclaims \u201cYou all killed him!....Not with bullets, or guns, with hate. Well now I can kill too, because now I have hate.\u201d That character in this musical works in a bridal shop and is arranged to marry (*) Chino. In a song from this musical, Rosalia praises her home island, while Anita describes \u201cthe hurricanes blowing\u201d and \u201cthe money owing.\u201d In one scene from a musical, two characters sing \u201cTonight\u201d while standing on a fire escape. For 10 points, name this Leonard Bernstein musical in which a group of Puerto Rican immigrants, the Sharks, fight with their rival gang, the Jets.", "answer": "West Side Story ", "subcategory": "Other Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>West Side Story</u></b>", "acceptable": ["West Side Story"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In one chapter of this novel, a car swerves to avoid a turtle in the road, though that turtle is later clipped by a truck. A preacher in this novel is self-described as \u201clousy with the spirit\u201d but considered an analogue to Jesus, and gives himself up after one character trips a cop chasing Floyd Knowles, who had asked for a (*) written contract. The protagonists of this novel are paid five cents per box while picking peaches as Jim Casy leads a strike outside the farm. Rose of Sharon gives birth to a stillborn baby at the end of, for 10 points, what John Steinbeck novel following the Joad family\u2019s voyage to California during the Dust Bowl?", "answer": "The Grapes of Wrath ", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>The Grapes of Wrath</u></b>", "acceptable": ["The Grapes of Wrath"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This actor played the recurring character \u201cBlizzard Man\u201d on Saturday Night Live. Along with Bill Hader and Shia LaBeouf, this actor starred in a sketch in which \u201cWhatcha Say\u201d plays after a gun is fired; he also appears as a Viking in \u201cNatalie\u2019s Rap\u201d and alongside Justin (*) Timberlake in three related digital shorts. A group featuring this actor released the albums Incredibad and Turtleneck &amp; Chain, and he played \u201cConnor4Real\u201d in their film Popstar. For 10 points, name this member of The Lonely Island, who stars alongside Terry Crews and Melissa Fumero as Detective Jake Peralta in Brooklyn Nine-Nine.", "answer": "David A.J. Samberg (or Andy Samberg) ", "subcategory": "Trash", "category": "Trash", "answer_formatted": "David A.J. <b><u>Samberg</u></b>", "acceptable": ["David A.J. Samberg"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or Andy Samberg"}, {"question": "The Hamilton Rating Scale and the Beck Inventory are surveys used to diagnose this disease, which is milder but longer-lasting in dysthymia. The monoamine theory of the causes of this disease is based on the role of tryptophan in producing (*) serotonin. Cognitive behavioral therapy was first developed to support patients with this disease, which is labelled \u201csecondary\u201d if it accompanies terminal or chronic conditions. For 10 points, name this mental disorder whose symptoms usually include loss of interest in activities, low energy, and low mood.", "answer": "clinical depression (or major depressive disorder; or MDD) ", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>clinical depression</u></b>", "acceptable": ["clinical depression"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or major depressive disorder; or MDD"}, {"question": "In 2019, the Maltese embassy to this country banned further graffiti on the Lennon Wall in this country\u2019s capital. In this country, the bones of thousands of individuals have been used to build decorations for the Sedlec Ossuary near the city of Kutna Hora. Cesky Krumlov is a historic city on the (*) Vltava River in this country. St. Vitus Cathedral is in a large castle complex in the capital of this country; that capital also contains Frank Gehry\u2019s Dancing House, Wenceslas Square, and the Charles Bridge. For 10 points, name this country with regions Moravia and Bohemia, and capital Prague.", "answer": "Czechia (or Czech Republic) ", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Czechia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Czechia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or Czech Republic"}, {"question": "One character in this poem is \u201cwrenched / with a woeful agony\u201d and asked \u201cwhat manner of man art thou?\u201d That character in this poem advises \u201che prayeth best, who loveth best\u201d to a figure who \u201cwent like one that hath been stunned\u201d and rose \u201ca sadder and a (*) wiser-man.\u201d The figures of Death and Life-in-Death play a game of dice in this poem, whose title figure narrates to the wedding guest about how there was \u201cwater, water everywhere / nor any drop to drink\u201d after shooting an albatross with a crossbow. For 10 points, name this Samuel Taylor Coleridge about a sailor\u2019s lengthy voyage.", "answer": "\u201cThe Rime of the Ancient Mariner\u201d ", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>\u201cThe Rime of the Ancient Mariner\u201d</u></b>", "acceptable": ["\u201cThe Rime of the Ancient Mariner\u201d"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Henry Lane Wilson, a U.S. ambassador to this country, is believed to have arranged the murder of its president as part of a 1913 coup known as the Ten Tragic Days. The third article of a constitution written in this country established (*) secular public education, while its 130th established separation of church and state, leading to the Cristero War. This country was led by Venustiano Carranza and Porfirio Diaz in a conflict sparked by Francisco Madero\u2019s Plan of San Luis Potosi. For 10 points, what country\u2019s 1910-1920 Revolution included armies led by Emiliano Zapata and Pancho Villa?", "answer": "Mexico (or United Mexican States) ", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Mexico</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Mexico"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or United Mexican States"}, {"question": "In Ovid\u2019s Fasti, this god co-rules Latium with Saturn after he is taught agriculture, and he raped the nymph of a sacred wood along the Tiber. The epithet \u201cpater\u201d was typically only given to this god, and religious rites often began by invoking him and ended with an invocation to Vesta. The gate of the Argiletum was named for this god, to whom the first verses of the Carmen Saliare are devoted. The gates to Rome\u2019s (*) Temple of this god were closed in peace and opened during war. For 10 points, name this Roman god of beginnings, endings, and similar transitions, who is often depicted with two faces.", "answer": "Janus ", "subcategory": "Mythology", "category": "Mythology", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Janus</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Janus"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In the presence of this ion, epoxides are opened at the more substituted carbon through an SN1-like mechanism. Tautomers are isomers that differ only by the location of this ion. Fischer esterification is catalyzed by this ion. This ion\u2019s standard reduction potential is (*) 0. This ion names the most commonly used type of NMR spectroscopy. A Br\u00f8nsted-Lowry acid is defined by its ability to donate this ion to a base, and it is produced in addition to hydroxide through the ionization of water. For 10 points, name this ion made up of a single proton.", "answer": "hydrogen ion (accept H+, accept H3O+ before \u201ctautomers\u201d; accept proton before mention) ", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>hydrogen ion</u></b>", "acceptable": ["hydrogen ion"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept H+, accept H3O+ before \u201ctautomers\u201d; accept proton before mention"}, {"question": "In 2019, divers found a temple and a large ceremonial ship in the ruins of an ancient city sunk by soil liquefaction in this modern-day country. The ruins of Heracleion are in this modern-day country, where people believed in a \u201clife-force\u201d called a ka and a soul called a ba. The game of (*) senet was developed in this country, where mudbrick mastabas were an early form of tomb. Canopic jars were used in the burial process of this modern-day country, where the Book of the Dead described the soul\u2019s journey to the afterlife. For 10 points, name this modern-day country that includes the ancient cities of Luxor, Memphis, and Giza.", "answer": "Arab Republic of Egypt (accept Ancient Egypt) ", "subcategory": "Ancient History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Arab Republic of Egypt</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Arab Republic of Egypt"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Ancient Egypt"}, {"question": "Robert and Helen Lynd are best known for a large field study of a community in this country, which was also the subject of a William Whyte book arguing most of its residents had collectivist rather than individualist ethics, leading them to be the title loyal figure. The \u201cmouth-rite,\u201d stone-walled \u201cshrine rooms,\u201d and a cultural hero who chopped down a (*) tree containing the Spirit of Truth, Notgnihsaw, are described in a satirical paper about society in this country. The Organization Man, Middletown, and \u201cBody Ritual among the Nacirema\u201d are studies of, for 10 points, what country also home to anthropologists Franz Boas and Margaret Mead?", "answer": "United States of America (or U.S.A.) ", "subcategory": "Social Science", "category": "Social Science", "answer_formatted": "United States of <b><u>America</u></b>", "acceptable": ["United States of America"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or U.S.A."}, {"question": "A movement that advocated for changes to this practice was started by William Lovett, who also founded the London Working Men\u2019s Association. The Newport Rising supported that movement, which was termed Chartism. The (*) Reform Act 1832 transformed this practice by removing \u201crotten boroughs,\u201d where very few people lived. At the 1913 Epsom Derby, King George V\u2019s horse killed Emily Davison, who advocated for the ability to participate in this practice. Suffragettes advocated for the expansion of, for 10 points, what practice?", "answer": "Voting (accept answers related to voting or elections; accept representation or suffrage before mention) ", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Voting</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Voting"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept answers related to voting or elections; accept representation or suffrage before mention"}, {"question": "This religion\u2019s idea that there are no permanent or unchanging souls is known as anatman, while objects without souls are not independent according to sunyata. In some branches of this religion,the Bardo is a type of purgatory where souls go before (*) reincarnation, in a cycle known as samsara. Nirodha is the renouncement of desire required in this religion, in which the last of the Four Noble Truths states that the Eightfold Path must be followed to end suffering and achieve Nirvana. For 10 points, name this Asian religion founded by a man who achieved enlightenment while sitting under a Bodhi tree.", "answer": "Buddhism (accept Mahayana Buddhism, Theravada Buddhism, Zen Buddhism, or Tibetan Buddhism; other specific types also acceptable) ", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Buddhism</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Buddhism"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Mahayana Buddhism, Theravada Buddhism, Zen Buddhism, or Tibetan Buddhism; other specific types also acceptable"}, {"question": "Space can be sacrificed in exchange for speed by \u201cunrolling\u201d these constructs. The implementation of one of these constructs requires a declaration, a conditional statement, and an incrementation. N2 [N-squared] runtimes are commonly created through (*) \u201cnested\u201d instances of these structures, which can be interrupted by break statements. \u201cWhile\u201d instances of these structures are typically used when the number of iterations is uncertain, as opposed to their \u201cfor\u201d type. For 10 points, name these sequences of instructions repeated several times in a program.", "answer": "loops (accept for loops before mention) ", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>loops</u></b>", "acceptable": ["loops"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept for loops before mention"}, {"question": "After speaking to his school\u2019s headmaster about a country\u2019s lack of Jews, one character in this novel remarks that \u201chistory is a nightmare from which I am trying to awake.\u201d In this novel, a biscuit is thrown at that character by The Citizen during an argument at Barney Kiernan\u2019s pub, and that character later watches a girl with a bad leg while at the (*) Sandymount Strand. This novel ends with one character remembering responding to a proposal with \u201cyes I said yes I will yes,\u201d and it begins with a meeting between Buck Mulligan and Stephen Daedalus. For 10 points, name this novel about a day in the life of Leopold Bloom, a work by James Joyce.", "answer": "Ulysses ", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Ulysses</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Ulysses"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The lupophon was invented after this composer wrote a part that calls for the heckelphone to play below its possible range. A descending A major scale is played to represent sunrise and an offstage brass section mimics a hunting party in a tone poem by this composer. \u201cWandering By the Brook\u201d and \u201cEntry Into the Forest\u201d are sections of his An (*) Alpine Symphony, while another of his tone poems uses the contrasting keys of B major and C major to represent humanity and the universe. The opening fanfare of that piece by this composer includes the \u201cC-G-C\u201d dawn motif later used in 2001: A Space Odyssey. For 10 points, name this composer of Also Sprach Zarathustra.", "answer": "Richard Strauss (prompt on Strauss) ", "subcategory": "Music", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Richard Strauss</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Richard Strauss"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on Strauss"}, {"question": "In this state, the Rum Riot led to the repeal of a prohibition law supported by Neal Dow, the mayor of its most populous city. After the Battle of Caribou in this state, Governor John Fairfield sent four regiments of militia to resolve a border dispute. Supporters of a \u201cHalf-Breed\u201d Presidential candidate from this state mocked his opponent with (*) \u201cMa, ma, where\u2019s my pa?\u201d while that candidate was called a \u201ccontinental liar\u201d from this state. James Blaine is from this state, which resolved the Aroostook War with New Brunswick. For 10 points, name this state admitted into the Union in 1820 as part of the Missouri Compromise, earlier part of Massachusetts.", "answer": "Maine ", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Maine</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Maine"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The equation that primarily governs these objects is applicable to all materials for a range below their yield strength. The displacement of one of these objects can be graphed as the mass times the second derivative of displacement with respect to time, divided by the negative of their namesake (*) constant. The frequency of these objects is equal to [read slowly] 1 divided by 2 pi all times the square root of that namesake constant divided by mass. These harmonic oscillators exert a force proportional to their displacement according to Hooke\u2019s law. For 10 points, name these objects that store mechanical energy when compressed.", "answer": "springs (prompt on simple harmonic oscillator before mention) ", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>springs</u></b>", "acceptable": ["springs"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on simple harmonic oscillator before mention"}, {"question": "In one novel by this author, a detective hears a confession in the apartment next door; that detective commits suicide after he is shot at by a woman he is pursuing. In another novel by this author, one character tells the story of Jesus (*) returning to earth and kissing the Inquisitor, and in another novel, the story of raising Lazarus from the dead is told by Sonya. Alexei, Ivan, and Dmitri are the three title characters of this author\u2019s The Brothers Karamazov. In another of his novels, the pawnbroker Alyona is murdered by Raskolnikov. For 10 points, name this author of Crime and Punishment.", "answer": "Fyodor Dostoyevsky ", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Fyodor <b><u>Dostoyevsky</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Fyodor Dostoyevsky"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A 50-foot-tall steel sculpture in this city of what is believed to be either a woman, an Afghan Hound, or a baboon was designed by Pablo Picasso. In this city\u2019s Crown Fountain, two towers facing each other on opposite sides of a pool display changing faces that have water squirt out of their mouths. A set of red arches forms Alexander Calder\u2019s (*) Flamingo sculpture in this city\u2019s Federal Plaza, while a 66-foot long steel sculpture designed by Anish Kapoor for a park in this city is titled Cloud Gate. For 10 points, name this city whose Millenium Park includes \u201cthe Bean.\u201d", "answer": "Chicago ", "subcategory": "Painting", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Chicago</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Chicago"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}]}